{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Emperor Wu Di of Han placed a monopoly on salt and this material. A pillar of this material was signed by King Chandra and notoriously resists corrosion. The Hittites created artifacts of this material. Abraham Darby created amethod to create the “pig”type of this substance usingcoke insteadof charcoal. and its “wrought” form was used to construct the Eiffel Tower. For ten points, name this metal whose use ended the Bronze Age.",
      "answer": "iron"
    },
    {
      "question": "During Europe’s industrial era, the most popular history of this country was an account by botanist Engelbert Kaempfer. The 26 martyrs were crucified in this country. After the San Felipe was shipwrecked near this country, its leader closed off most of its ports to Spanish and Portuguese missionaries and forced its Christian population to become Kakure [ka-koo-ray], or hidden. For ten points, name this country where Christianity once flourished around Nagasaki.",
      "answer": "Japan"
    },
    {
      "question": "William Thomas Turner attempted to prevent this disaster, which occurred near the Old Head of Kinsale. The Cunard Company was prosecuted for its negligence surrounding this event, since it failed to reveal that munitions had been placed in storage. William Jennings Bryan resigned as Secretary of State because he felt Woodrow Wilson was too strong-handed in his reaction to, for ten points, what 1915 event in which a British ocean liner was torpedoed by a German U-boat?",
      "answer": "sinking of or attack on, etc. the RMS Lusitania"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Weir invented a device that uses this mineral to compress materials to extremely high pressures. This mineral is the ideal crystal for ATR infrared spectroscopy. These minerals are often found in kimberlite pipes, which are named for a town in South Africa. For ten points, name this allotrope of carbon, a mineral created under extremely high temperatures and pressure that defines the value of 10 on Mohs’ scale of hardness.",
      "answer": "diamonds"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this period, accused parties were ordered to prove their innocence by the Law of 22 Prairial, which strengthened the Law of Suspects. This period came to an end when the Battle of Fleurus helped trigger the Thermidorian Reaction against one of this period’s leaders. The Committee of Public Safety took control during this period, which ended with Maximilien Robespierre’s own execution. For ten points, name this year-long phase of the French Revolution in many political enemies were guillotined.",
      "answer": [
        "Reign of Terror or The Terror",
        "La Terreur"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to defecting to the Confederacy, Franklin Buchanan was the first superintendent of this institution’s academy. George Bancroft founded the training center for this military force. Two rival members of this force dueled in 1820, with James Barron killing Stephen Decatur. Another early leader of this force, John Paul Jones, led the Bon Homme Richard when he declared “I have not yet begun to fight!” For ten points, name this military force whose academy is based in Annapolis, Maryland on the Chesapeake Bay.",
      "answer": [
        "US Navy",
        "word forms and elaborations like US Naval Academy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Scottish financier John Law advertised land claims along this river, triggering a bubble named after this river in the French court. A Native American culture named for this river constructed the mounds at Cahokia. Robert de La Salle claimed the entirety of this river’s basin for France, and its northern reaches were explored by Jacques Marquette and Louis Jolliet. The French territory of Louisiana was centered around, for ten points, what river that empties into the Gulf of Mexico near New Orleans?",
      "answer": "Mississippi River"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the originally planned climax of Men in Black II, these structures were to release a swarm of UFOs. A helicopter is caught in a web between these structures in an original trailer for the first Tobey Maguire Spiderman film. The 2008 film Man on Wire documents Philippe Petit’s illegal 1974 walk between these structures on a high-wire. Several early 21st century films edited out, for ten points, what Manhattan buildings that were attacked on September 11th?",
      "answer": [
        "World Trade Center 1 and/or 2",
        "Twin Towers and other descriptive answers of the two tallest bulidings in the WTC complex"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first site to establish this industry in the U.S. was the Beverly Manufactory. A man nicknamed “the traitor” memorized the designs of British equipment used in this industry and recreated it in the U.S.; that man was Samuel Slater. The Waltham-Lowell system placed young girls in this industry in boardinghouses in Massachusetts and Rhode Island. The product of Eli Whitney’s gin was used in, for ten points, what industry that converted cotton into shirts and pants?",
      "answer": [
        "textile industry",
        "clothing industry",
        "garment industry",
        "cotton industry before read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Hugh Trenchard is nicknamed the “father of” this military force, which sustained heavy casualties in Bloody April during the Battle of Arras. The efforts of this military force prompted the declaration “Never was so much owed by so many to so few.” This force employed the Sopwith Camel during World War I and the Supermarine Spitfire during World War II. For ten points, name this military force that battled the Luftwaffe to defend cities like Coventry and London.",
      "answer": [
        "Royal Air Force or RAF",
        "Royal Flying Corps",
        "descriptions of the air force of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland,",
        "British Air Force,",
        "similar"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer included movements titled “The Absence” and “The Return” in a piano sonata inspired by his patron Archduke Rudolph fleeing Vienna, Les Adieux. He wrote a set of 33 variations on a waltz he supposedly dismissed as a “cobbler’s patch.” This composer of the Diabelli Variations also wrote a sonata “quasi una fantasia” that reminded Ludwig Rellstab of an object shining over Lake Lucerne. For ten points, name this German composer of Fu¨r Elise and the Moonlight Sonata.",
        "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Archduke Rudolph had to flee Vienna due to the actions of what man who was initially planned to be the dedicatee of Beethoven’s Symphony no. 3, Eroica?",
        "answer": [
          "Napoleon Bonaparte",
          "either",
          "both names",
          "Napoleon I"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man once threw his alcoholic friend John Collins into a river when he refused to row a boat. This man founded an intellectual group known as either the Leather Apron Society or the Junto [jun-toh]. In Boston, this man used the pseudonym Silence Dogood to send letters to The New-England Courant; after he moved to Philadelphia, he switched newspapers to work on The Pennsylvania Gazette. For ten points, name this founding father who wrote and published Poor Richard’s Almanack.",
        "answer": "Benjamin Franklin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1754, Franklin’s Pennsylvania Gazette published this political cartoon advocating for colonial unity. This cartoon identifies eight regions, including New England but not Georgia, as segments of a cut snake.",
        "answer": [
          "Join,",
          "Die"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This program’s effects were first tested at an artificial community in Chayashan, where all wages were replaced by “work points.” Sparrows were systematically killed in this program, as the government sought to eliminate the “Four Pests.” 30 million people may have perished in the world’s deadliest famine as a result of this program, which encouraged farmers to establish backyard steel furnaces. For ten points, name this 1958 initiative in which Mao Zedong attempted to industrialize China.",
        "answer": [
          "Great Leap Forward",
          "da yue jin",
          "Second Five Year Plan"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Great Leap Forward ran concurrently with this other program, in which Mao Zedong invited others to criticize his policies. Later, he abruptly turned course and jailed the “rightist” dissidents.",
        "answer": [
          "Hundred Flowers movement",
          "Baihua yundong"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A character created by this author is nicknamed “We don’t do that” after he is punished for refusing to carry a rifle in a parade. This author devoted one chapter to each of 100 years in his book My Century. This author, who admitted to being a member of the Waffen-SS in his memoir Peeling the Onion, wrote a novel in which Oskar Matzerath refuses to grow past the age of three. For ten points, name this German author of The Tin Drum.",
        "answer": "Gunter Grass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Grass’s The Tin Drum, Cat and Mouse, and Dog Years form a trilogy named after this Polish city that existed as an independent city-state between 1920 and 1939.",
        "answer": [
          "Danzig Trilogy",
          "Gdansk"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s winning commander allegedly declared “by tomorrow, I shall have gained a peerage or Westminster Abbey” before leading the Vanguard into combat. After this battle, Armand Blanquet [blan-kay] was sacked for surrendering the undamaged Franklin. Poorly stored paint caused an explosion aboard the L’Orient [lor-ee-ahn] in this battle, which was fought in Aboukir Bay. Napoleon’s expedition withdrew from North Africa shortly after losing, for ten points, what 1798 naval battle to Horatio Nelson in Egypt?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Nile",
          "Battle of Aboukir Bay before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of the Nile was preceded by this land battle where Napoleon used squares to thwart Ottoman Mamluk cavalry. At this battle, Napoleon told his men that “40 centuries of history look down upon you.”",
        "answer": "Battle of the Pyramids"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these provinces boasted the largest Roman baths outside of Rome after Constantine renovated Augusta Treverorum. Imperial Roman influence in these provinces began when Domitius Ahenobarbus was summoned to aid the city of Massilia. This region, which was divided into the provinces of Belgica, Aquitania, and Celtica, was conquered when a circumvallation wall helped defeat the Averni tribe at Alesia. Julius Caesar conquered, for ten points, what ancient region in modern-day France?",
        "answer": [
          "provinces of Gaul or Gallia",
          "Gallia Belgica",
          "Gallia Narbonensis after “Domitius” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Gallic Pont du Gard was an example of what type of Roman structure that serviced Nimes [neem]?",
        "answer": "aqueducts"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man rebuked Henry Proctor, saying “I conquer to save, you [conquer] to kill” after their joint army perpetrated a massacre of prisoners at Fort Meigs. The New Madrid earthquake was interpreted by locals as a sign to join this man, whose death at the Battle of the Thames led to the dissolution of his tribal confederacy and its alliance with Great Britain. For ten points, name this chief of the Shawnee who fought the United States before and during the War of 1812 but was absent from the disastrous Battle of Tippecanoe.",
        "answer": "Tecumseh"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tecumseh journeyed West in a failed attempt to ally with this five member tribal group. This group, composed of the Cherokee, Creek, Seminole, Choctaw and Chickasaw, received its name because it adopted Western customs.",
        "answer": "Five Civilized Tribes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler was denounced as illegitimate by Pope Pius V in the bull Regnans in Excelsis after refusing to persecute minority religions. The use of fireships at Gravelines [grah-vel-een] allowed this ruler to stave off enemy invasion. While preparing for an imminent attack from the Spanish Armada, this ruler inspired the troops at Tilbury by claiming to possess the “body of a weak, feeble woman” but the “heart and stomach of a king.” Anne Boleyn was the mother of, for ten points, what Virgin Queen of 16th century England?",
        "answer": "Elizabeth I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During Elizabeth’s fight against the Spanish Armada, she hired this privateer who attacked the Spanish fleet at Cadiz and later circumnavigated the globe for England.",
        "answer": "Sir Francis Drake"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "U.S.-French Relations",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1803 land purchase in which the U.S. acquired much of the Midwest.",
          "answer": "Louisiana Purchase"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for ceasing trade to a foreign nation, as the U.S. did to France with an 1807 act.",
          "answer": [
            "embargo",
            "Embargo Act"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1797 incident in which bribes were demanded of three American diplomats.",
          "answer": "XYZ Affair"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle, a defeat for John Burgoyne in the Revolutionary War, that convinced France to support the American Revolution.",
          "answer": "Battle of Saratoga"
        },
        {
          "question": "American politician who co-names an 1928 anti-war pact with French minister Aristide Briand.",
          "answer": "Frank Kellogg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Controversial 18th century French “citizen” ambassador who wanted to bring America into war with Britain.",
          "answer": "Edmond-Charles Genet"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unofficial war between the U.S. and France that was ended by the Conventions of 1800.",
          "answer": "Quasi War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Diplomat who negotiated a loan from France to the Confederacy and who was captured along with James Mason in the Trent Affair.",
          "answer": "John Slidell"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Labor and Revolt in the Nineteenth Century",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Philosopher of labor who worked with Engels on the Communist Manifesto.",
          "answer": "Karl Marx"
        },
        {
          "question": "Period of urban migration and swift technological improvement that began in Britain in the early 19th century.",
          "answer": "Industrial Revolution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which Austria and Hungary gave up serfdom and revolutions occurred all over Europe during the “Spring of Nations.”",
          "answer": "1848"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where an 1871 socialist “Commune” was suppressed following its country’s loss to Prussia.",
          "answer": "Paris Commune"
        },
        {
          "question": "GermanKaiser,anemployerofOttovonBismarck,whoseattemptedassassinationsledtoacrackdown on socialists.",
          "answer": "Wilhelm I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massacre of British protesters in 1819 that led to the Six Acts, restricting protests.",
          "answer": "Peterloo Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hungarian revolutionary who briefly led the country and toured the United States after being exiled.",
          "answer": "Lajos Kossuth de Udvard et Kossuthfalva or Louis Kossuth"
        },
        {
          "question": "German customs union that bound its states together prior to the country’s unification.",
          "answer": "Zollverein"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Australia",
      "prompt": "Name the....",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Australia, a planned city designed in the early 20th century.",
          "answer": "Canberra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern city that is home to Botany Bay, where the British first landed in eastern Australia.",
          "answer": "Sydney"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jorn Utzon-designed arts center in that city, known for its white concrete shells.",
          "answer": "Sydney Opera House"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Territory city that was the site of the first and largest Japanese bombing raid on Australia in World War II.",
          "answer": "Darwin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wild animal that killed two-month-old Azaria Chamberlain, whose parents were initially blamed for her 1980 “murder.”",
          "answer": "dingo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bushranger whose gang robbed banks and trains until a final shootout at Glenrowan in 1880.",
          "answer": "Edward “Ned” Kelly"
        },
        {
          "question": "1808 rebellion, the only successful armed revolution in Australia, that deposed William Bligh.",
          "answer": "Rum Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "1854 rebellion of gold miners in Ballarat.",
          "answer": "Eureka Stockade rebellion"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While in office, this man vetoed the Rivers and Harbors Act for its high cost. Robert Todd Lincoln finished his service as Secretary of War under this president. This man was initially distrusted for being a (20 pts)",
        "“Stalwart” Republican and supporting patronage, but he broke with his old boss Roscoe Conkling by reversing that stance and passing the (10 pts)",
        "Pendleton Act to reform civil service. This man served as Vice President under a man who was assassinated by Charles Guiteau. For ten points, name this President who succeeded James Garfield."
      ],
      "answer": "Chester Alan Arthur"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people reached their golden age under Simeon I, who waged successful campaigns against their Khazar enemies. Scholars belonging to this ethnic group developed the first Cyrillic script. Krum, a ruler of these people, allegedly lined the (20 pts)",
        "skull of Nikephoros I with silver and used it as a drinking cup. After losing the Battle of Kleidion, these people were supposedly blinded en masse by the Byzantine emperor Basil II, who then became known as a (10 pts)",
        "“slayer” of them. For ten points, name this nomadic European ethnic group, the namesake of a modern country whose capital is Sofia."
      ],
      "answer": "Bulgars"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these documents claims found that a Swiss lawyer named Dieter Neupert was directly in contact with the Royal family of Qatar. A reporter for the Munich-based publication SZ broke the story about these documents, some of which focused on (20 pts)",
        "Sigmundur Gunnlaugson of Iceland. The law firm Mossack Fonseca created these documents, whose revelation prompted David (10 pts)",
        "Cameron to admit that he profited from offshore accounts held by his father. For ten points, name this set of over 11 million documents that were leaked in 2016 and linked illegal shell companies to prominent figures."
      ],
      "answer": "Panama Papers"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the disposal of this man’s body, his assassins drove a Fiat truck into the Koptyaki forest only to realize they had only one shovel. This man received notice that Leonid Sednev would be leaving his entourage shortly before he was (20 pts)",
        "moved into the basement of the Ipatiev House in Yekaterinburg. (10 pts)",
        "Anastasia was speculated to have survived the murder of this man and his family. Fearing the advancing White Army, the Bolsheviks executed, for ten points, what final Russian tsar?"
      ],
      "answer": "Nicholas II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One artist from this movement painted the f-holes of a violin on a classical Ingres [AHNG] nude and experimented with photograms now named after him. The New York (20 pts)",
        "Armory show emboldened another artist in this movement to exhibit everyday objects, such as snow shovels and bottle racks, as (10 pts)",
        "“readymades;” that artist from this movement also signed “R. Mutt” on a urinal. Man Ray and Marcel Duchamp belonged to, for ten points, what avant-garde art movement that flourished after World War I?"
      ],
      "answer": "Dadaism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Tensions leading up to this event were heightened due to similar events at the Tele-Star, the Checkerboard, the Snake Pit, and the Sewer. In the aftermath of this event, Maria Ritter stated her second biggest fear was being shown in the newspaper (20 pts)",
        "wearing her mother’s dress. This event was described as the “Hairpin Drop Heard Around the World” by the Mattachine Society. This event took place at an establishment owned by the (10 pts)",
        "Genovese crime family that operated without a liquor license. For ten points, name this 1969 riot in Greenwich [gren-itch] Village, New York that began with a police raid on the namesake gay bar."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Stonewall Inn riots",
        "equivalents for riot"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. A pessimistic analysis of this event was criticized by Etienne Mantoux’s [eh-tee-ehn mahn-too’s] Carthaginian Peace. Government price controls developed in the aftermath of this event led to (20 pts)",
        "hyperinflation, one of this event’s Economic Consequences detailed by John Maynard Keynes; that analysis of this event was cited by the (10 pts)",
        "“irreconcilables,” who thus argued against joining the League of Nations as part of this event. For ten points, name this event that led to the creation of the Weimar Republic and the imposition of severe reparations against the defeated Germany."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "the agreements to end World War I",
        "descriptive answers relating to the peace process that ended World War I",
        "the signing of the Treaty of Versailles",
        "the Paris Peace Conference",
        "descriptions that relate to the US’s rejection of Versailles/signing a separate peace to end World War I, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Samuel Sharpe led a revolt in this country against the UK during the Baptist War. This country’s Cockpit Country was the home of the first of the Maroon Wars. An activist born in this country founded the (20 pts)",
        "Black Star Line as part of his Back to Africa movement. This country’s Port Royal grew via frequent use by (10 pts)",
        "pirates like Henry Morgan, but was rocked by a 1692 earthquake. Marcus Garvey was born in, for ten points, what Caribbean island country where earthquake survivors founded the city of Kingston?"
      ],
      "answer": "Jamaica"
    }
  ]
}